Guide to the French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
French Revolution and Napoleonic period manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
4606
1027 items.
Original documents, mostly autograph signed letters (ALS).
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Manuscript documents and correspondence, mainly government documents, most of them covering the period 1788-1815.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
A diplomat, historian, statesman, and co-founder and first president of Cornell University, Andrew Dickson White (1832-1918) was also the first to teach French (and German) modern history at University-level in the United States -- at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, and at Cornell. His lectures were largely based on original documents from his private collection, which form the bulk of this present set of documents. His developed summaries (see, for example, 4606 Bd. Ms. 12 ++, "Lettres de cachet") show both his mastery of the French language, and his pedagogical concerns while building his collection, not a mere private hobby.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Manuscript documents and correspondence, mainly government documents, including 6 volumes of bound manuscripts, concerning mostly the administration of the French government throughout the Revolution, be it at the national level (especially the Comité de Salut Public and the Comité de Sûreté Générale et de Surveillance in 1793-5), at the "département" level, or at the local level (esp. Paris and Toulon in 1793-4).
Also included are a 1789 letter by Brissot to the English Abolitionist Society expressing his views on slavery; a contemporary Italian translation of the Testament of Louis XVI (guillotined in January 1793); and the first two drafts of Gracchus Babeuf's "Précis d'un projet de cadastre perpétuel", a technical essay that he wrote in 1787 in response to Calonne's proposal for a general land tax.
Post-revolutionary documents cover a wide range of subjects, such as military and naval history, or the education and sociability of the French elites. Noticeable here are: a letter concerning Menou, a French general who had converted to Islam and married an Egyptian (veiled) woman, 1802; a letter from Napoleon to Berthier containing strategic instructions for the battle of Wagram, 1809; a letter from Fontanes, then "grand master of the University," deriding the idea of a Professorship of Poetry in France (c.1810); a letter from four Napoleon's marshals trying to negotiate a deal on their income-providing "dotations" with the great powers assembled in Vienna, in late September 1814; a letter from Richelieu on "the White Terror," 1815; a statement by Grégoire (1820); and a letter by Nesselrode, given and annotated by A.D. White.
Autograph manuscripts followed by a * come from the Bowe Collection #4624, "Miscellaneous French Correspondence and Documents," given to Cornell by Arthur and Mary M. Dean in April 1976, and now merged with #4606. A couple of documents were purchased and added to the collection in 2008-9 (box 3, folder 31, and box 5, folder 14).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Babeuf, Gracchus, 1760-1797.; Bailly, Jean-Sylvain, 1736-1793.; Barbé-Marbois, François, marquis de, 1745-1837.; Barras, Paul, 1755-1829.; Bonaparte family.; Brissot de Warville, J.-P. (Jacques-Pierre), 1754-1793.; Campan, Mme (Jeanne-Louise-Henriette), 1752-1822.; Carnot, Lazare, 1753-1823.; Chateaubriand, François-René, vicomte de, 1768-1848.; Clauzel, Bertrand, comte, 1772-1842.; Custine, Adam Philippe de, 1740-1793.; Dampierre, Auguste Henri Marie de, 1756-1793.; Daru, Pierre-Antoine-Noël-Bruno, comte, 1767-1829.; Dillon, Arthur, 1750-1794.; Fontanes, Jean Pierre Louis de, 1758-1821.; Fouché, Joseph, duc d'Otrante, 1763-1820.; Gouges, Olympe de, 1748-1793.; Grégoire, Henri, 1750-1831.; Kellermann, François Christophe, 1735-1820.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834.; Louis XVI, King of France, 1754-1793.; Menou, Jacques, 1750-1810.; Napoleon I, Emperor of the French, 1769-1821.; Necker, Jacques, 1732-1804.; Ney, Michel, 1769-1815.; Pétion, Jérôme, 1756-1794.; Poniatowski, Jo´zef, ksiaze, 1816-1873.; Richelieu, Armand-Emmanuel du Plessis, duc de, 1766-1822.; Robespierre, Maximilien de, 1758-1794.; Ségur, Louis-Philippe, comte de, 1753-1830.; Sieyès, Emmanuel Joseph, 1748-1836.; Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, prince de Bénévent, 1754-1838.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.
Subjects:
Abolitionists--France.; Abolitionists--Great Britain.; Catholic Church--France.; Finance, Public--France.; France--History--Revolution, 1789-1799.; Jews--France--History--18th century.; Local government--France.; Military history, Modern--19th century.; Slavery.; France--History--Reign of Terror, 1793-1794.
Places:
Egypt--History.; France--Foreign relations--United States.; France--History--Revolution, 1789-1799.; France--Politics and government--1789-1799.; France--History--Revolution, 1789-1799--Economic aspects.; Italy--History.; Paris (France)--History--1789-1799.; Bastille.; Paris (France)--History.; Poland--History--1795-1815.; Provence (France)--History.; Toulon (France)--History.; United States--Foreign relations--France.
Form and Genre Terms:
Caricatures.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Letterheads.; Lettres de cachet.; Seals.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Many items have interesting allegorical letterheads. NB: the authenticity of a couple of documents (signaled by [?]) is dubious. In addition to the letters (some of them annotated by the collectors or by librarians), many folders contain engraved and lithographed portraits, as well as notes written by collectors or archivists.
Related collections at Cornell include the Ben Grauer, Charles X, Lafayette, Laforte, Lavoisier, and Maurepas Collections, and the Pamphlets, Graphics, Newspapers, and Books components of the French Revolution Collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- Autograph manuscripts
  - A-Ber (Box 1)
    - Abrantès, Laure Pernon Junot, Duchesse d', ALS to [Soult?], 23 Nov. 1834; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves + 8 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1)
      ALS with translation plus a second letter with translation. Included are 3 portraits of the Duchesse plus photograph of the house where she lived and 4 leaves of miscellaneous material.
    - Abrial, Comte Andre Joseph ALS to the Prefet of Finistere, 3 Sept. 1802; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 2)
      ALS in French
    - Ameilhon, Hubert Pascal, to Suard, 10 July 1806; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
      ALS in French mentioning Mme de Genlis
    - Andréossy, Comte Antoine, to Barbier du Bocage, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General d'Anglemont, to Alexandre Berthier, 19 June 1802; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Angoulême, Louis Antoine, Duc d', to the French Ambassador in London, 26 April 1814; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Anthoine, François, to ?, 20 Oct. 1777; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Aubernon, Commissaire Ordonnateur des Guerres in Milan, to Latrieux, 2 Sept. 1800; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Aubert-Dubayet, General Francois, to Lauchere, 10 July 1795; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 9)
      ALS in French plus a second letter with translation. Included is a portrait of Aubert-Dubayet
    - Aubry, Francois, 14 Sept. 1796; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 10)
      ALS in French, annotated and signed by Barras, Carnot, La Revellière-Lepeaux, and Reubell
    - Audouin, Xavier, to ?, 2 Sept. 1800; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Auguereau, Pierre Francois, to the Commissioners of the Executive Directory in Charge of the Department of the Pyrenées Orientales, 25 April 1799; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 1, Folder 12)
      ALS in French +a second letter [1796] + a translation + four portraits of Auguereau
    - Aultanne, General d', to Commissaire Ordonnateur en Chef Chambon, 14 June 1806; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 14)
      ALS in French plus translation
    - Babad, Father Peter [of the Society of St. Sulpice in Baltimore], to Payne Todd [the man charged with the care of the Madisons' estate in Montpelier, Vt.], 14 February 1819; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 15)
      ALS in French. NB: Babad was the first scholar to teach a Portuguese course in an American University. In 1819 he was trying to raise funds to publish the first Portuguese grammar in the USA.
    - Babeuf, Francois Noël dit Gracchus, to Antoine Lamy, 21 Febr. 1791; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 16)
      [Roye] ALS in French: "J'ai la satisfaction de voir que l'Assemblee nationale a adopte la plus forte partie de mon systeme et de mes idees [sur] la contribution fonciere et la contribution personnelle."
    - Babeuf, Francois Noël dit Gracchus, to ?, n.d. [1794?]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 17)
      ALS in French, plus translation
    - Babeuf, Francois Noël dit Gracchus, 2 Sept. 1800; 1 bd. ms. + 1 bd. ms. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      The manuscripts are the first two drafts of a technical essay entitled "Précis d'un projet de cadastre perpétuel", written in 1787 by Babeuf, then a "feudist" in Picardy, in response to Minister Calonne's proposal for a general land tax. The first draft is in the hand of Babeuf but lacks about fourteen pages in the middle of the text. The second draft is in secraterial hand with additions by the author, and it is complete. A greatly expanded version of the work was published in late 1789, the year Babeuf drafted the cahier de doléances for the electors of the bailliage of Roye, demanding the abolition of feudal rights.
    - Bachelu, Gilbert, to Prince Louis Bonaparte, 2 Sept. 1800; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 19)
      ALS in French, plus translation, a portrait, and notes
    - Bailly, Jean Sylvain, to the Dames de la Communauté de la Providence, 31 Dec. 1789; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 20)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and portraits of Bailly
    - Baird, David,, to [Evans?], May 1817; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 21)
      ALS in English
    - Balland, General, to General Chabran, 23 April 1797; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Baraguey d'Hilliers, Louis, to Clarke, Duc de Feltre, 2 Sept. 1814; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Barante, Baron Prosper [in his capacity as Préfet of Vendée], to Bigot de Préameneu, 12 March 1814; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 24)
      ALS in French, plus notes on the religious situation in the Vendée
    - Barbaroux, Charles, to a Lady, 2 Sept. 1800; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Manuscript in French [2 p.of light verses, for a lady], plus translation
    - Barbé-Marbois, François de, to "le citoyen Burnel, agent du Directoire executif"*, October 1799; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 26a)
      ALS in French. B-M. is requesting a three-months extension of his "sojourn" in Cayenne, where he had been deported on a trumped charge after the "royalist coup d'Etat" of the 18th Fructidor year V (4 September 1797), and where he is now a member of the local government.
    - Barbé-Marbois, François de, to a forest administrator in Noyon, 18 August 1806; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 26b)
    - Barbé-Marbois, François de, to M. ... Portalis, [between 1807 &1815]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 26c)
      ALS in French, making an appointment to see him; plus a portrait of Barbé-Marbois
    - Barentin, Charles de [in his capacity as Président de la Cour des Aides] to the Comte d'Artois, 8 May 1788; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Document in French [incomplete copy]
    - Baudelaire, François, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 28)
      [Paris, Senat] ALS in French. N.B.: A high-ranking civil-servant, François Baudelaire was the poet's father.
    - Beaufort, General, to the Citoyen Dufresnoy, s.d. [1796/97]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Beauharnais, Eugene de, to Clarke, Duc de Feltre, 16 January 1814; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 30)
      ALS in French, plus portraits
    - Beauharnais, Augusta-Amelie, to Mme Lefebvre, 12 August 1829; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Belliard, General Augustin {French Governor of Madrid], to ?, 12 June 1809; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Belliard, General Augustin, to Clarke, Duc de Feltre, 1813; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 33)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter and a portrait of Belliard
    - Benezech, Pierre [Minister of the Interior], to Labarthe, 15 August 1796; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 34)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter and biographical notes
    - Béranger, Pierre Jean de, to ?, s.d. [1844]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 35)
      ALS in French, plus a portrait of Béranger
    - Bernadotte, Jean Baptiste, to General Girardon, n.d. [1801]; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 36)
      ALS in French, plus portraits of Bernadotte, also known as King John XIV of Sweden.
    - Bernard, General, to Mr. King, 1829; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 9 leaves (Box 1, Folder 37)
      [Washington] ALS in French, plus a second letter, plus biographical notes
    - Berthier, General Alexandre, to General Dumas, 1799-1809; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 4 leaves + 6 leaves (Box 1, Folder 38)
      ALS in French, plus four other letters, plus portraits of Berthier and biographical information
    - Bertrand, General Henri Gratien, to ?, 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 39)
      ALS in French, plus portraits of Bertrand
    - Bertrand de Molleville, Antoine François, to Napoleon I, n.d. [1814?]; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 40)
      ALS in French [petition asking the Emperor to provide him financial support; with an autograph note by the Count de Las Cases], with a full translation.
  - Bes-Cd (Box 2)
    - Bessières, Jean-Baptiste, to the Préfet de la Seine, 31 August 1809; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Beurnonville, Marquis de, to M. d'Hauterive, 20 August 1818; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 2)
      ALS in French, plus a portrait of Beurnonville and biographical notes
    - Bézard, 1794; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 3)
      [Nantes] Document in French
    - Bigarré, Baron Auguste, to ?, 28 May 1814; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 4a)
    - Bignon, Louis Pierre Edouard, to XXX*, 2 Oct. 1803; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 4b)
      ALS in French requesting payment to General Beurnonville and to himself
    - Bignon, Louis Pierre Edouard [French representative/"chargé d'affaires" in Cracow, Poland] to Maret*, 22 April 1813; 3 leaves (Box 2, Folder 4c)
      ALS in French about the military and diplomatic situation in Poland: in particular, Bignon explains the necessity for Prince Jósef Antoni Poniatowski, War Minister of the Great-Duchy of Warsaw and ally of the French, to evacuate Cracow "le 28 de ce mois, [car] les vivres et les munitions lui manquent, l'infanterie n'a pas plus de 60 cartouches par homme, et l'artillerie n'est approvisionnée encore que dans une proportion inférieure" (P. left Krakow on 5th May 1813 and crossed the Polish/Austrian border on 9 May 1813). He writes about the incorporation of the Lithuanian guard into the 1st regiment of Polish lancers, which caused "une sensation défavorable, comme une indication que S.M. ne voulait plus prendre d'intérêt à rien de ce qui concerne la Lithuanie"; finally, Bignon comments on a visit of Prince Antoni Henryk Radziwill to Vienna, and mentions "la réception que nous lui avons faite à Cracovie".
    - Bigot de Préameneu, Félix Julien Jean, to the "citoyen Guillon d'Assas, ancien jurisconsulte"*, n.d. [1802]; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 4d)
    - Bigot de Préameneu, Félix Julien Jean [Minister of Cults] [copy of a circular to the bishops]*, 7 December 1808; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 4e)
      ALS in French: a solemn Te Deum will be sung in churches after the French victory in Madrid, "sauvée des mains des brigands."
    - Biron, Armand Louis, Duc de Lauzun, 22 June 1793; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Document in French, plus translation
    - Biron, Armand Louis, Duc de Lauzun, to M. de Sartine [Minister of the Navy], 20 July1779; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 6)
      ALS in French [asks permission to cut a tree owned by and destined for the French Navy], plus translation and a portrait of Biron.
    - Blumenstein, C.M.. to the Mayor of Vienne [France], 8 June 1808; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Bochart de Saron, Jean Baptiste, to M. de Villedeuil, 28 May 1814; 1 leaf + 1 leaf +2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 8)
      ALS in French [about the death of the Dauphin], plus translation, and biographical notes
    - Boissy d'Anglas, Francois de, to ?, 16 August 1822; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 9)
      ALS in French, plus portraits of Boissy d'Anglas
    - Bonaparte, Lucien, 19 August 1797; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Document in French, plus portraits of Lucien Bonaparte and his wife.
    - Bonaparte, Lucien [in his capacity as Minister of the Interior], 5 May 1800; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Bondy, Comte Pierre de, to the Préfet de la Seine, 2 June 1806; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Borghèse, Pauline [née Bonaparte], to the Comte de Lavalette, 10 Nov. 1813; 1 leaf + 2 leaves + 6 leaves (Box 2, Folder 13)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and portraits of the Princess
    - Bouchotte, Jean-Baptiste, 29 July 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Satisfecit delivered to Caporal Philibert in French, plus translation
    - Bouchotte, Jean-Baptiste, 15 September1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Bouchotte, Jean-Baptiste, 29 July 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Satisfecit delivered to Caporal Lefevre in French, plus translation
    - Botta, Carlo, to his wife Antonietta, 13 May 1816; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 2, Folder 17)
      ALS in French, plus biographical notes and a portrait
    - Bougainville, Louis-Antoine, Comte de, to Fontanes, 29 August 1808; 1 leaf + 3 leaves + 3 leaves (Box 2, Folder 18)
      ALS in French, plus portraits of Bougainville and notes
    - Bouillé, Comte de, to M. de La Tour-Maubourg, 5 July 1818; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 19a)
    - Boulay de La Meurthe, Antoine, to M. de Montesquiou*, 25 September 1808; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 19b)
      ALS in French about "domaines nationaux"
    - Bourdon de Vatry, Marc Antoine, to the "Président de la Commune", 11 March 1793; 1 leaf+ 4 leaves + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 20)
      ALS in French [about a victim of the Terror, Prince Wittgenstein], plus translation, and notes
    - Bourguignon-Dumolard [Juge au Tribunal Criminel], to Lhermine, 21 April 1803; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 21)
      ALS in French, plus notes
    - Bourrienne, Louis, to the Director of the Imprimerie Nationale, 14 June 1799; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Brissac, Duc de, to M. de Saint-James, 2 Febr.1782; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 23)
      ALS in French, plus translation and notes
    - Brissot dit de Warville, Jacques, to James Philips [English Abolitionist Society], 27 June 1789; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 24)
      ALS in English about the necessity to "raise the spirits of your countrymen [with regards to] the abolition of negro trade"; mentions Henry Thornton, Lavallée's novel "Le Nègre comme il y a peu de blancs", and two pamphlets by Brissot enclosed in the letter.
    - Bretagne/Brittany, Remontrances de la Noblesse de, 26 May 1788; 1 cahier (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Document in French [copy]
    - Broussier, General Comte Jean-Baptiste, to Berthier, 11 October 1804; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 26)
      ALS in French, plus a portrait of Broussier
    - Bruix, Eustache, to the "Citoyen Pottier, negociant", 9 August 1798; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 27)
      ALS in French, plus a portrait and notes
    - Brune, General, to the Payeur-général de l'Armée d'Italie, 5 March 1801; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 28)
      ALS in French, plus portraits of Brune
    - Buniva, Inspecteur General de la Santé Publique in Piemont, to the Members of the Institut in Paris, 30 Dec. 1802; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 29)
      ALS in French [sends 61 volumes containing the minutes of the Société subalpine d'agriculture.]
    - Cabanis, Pierre, to M. Suard, 8 June 1803; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Cacault, Adjudant Commissaire, to the Payeur-Général de l'Armee d'Italie, n.d. [1801]; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Cadet-Gassicourt, Charles-Louis, to the Commandant de la Force Armée de la Section du Mont-Blanc, 16 February 1795; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 32)
      ALS in French, plus translation and note
    - Calon, General Etienne, to the Directeur du Dépôt Général de la Guerre, 3 June 1795; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Calonne, Charles de, to the Comtesse de Lowendal, March 1785; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Cambacérès, Jean-Jacques-Régis, to Robert*, 1795; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 34a)
    - Cambacérès, Jean-Jacques-Régis, to Lavalette *, 30 Oct. 1808; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 34b)
      ALS in French re: the delivery and pick-up of the government mail in the absence of the Emperor
    - Cambacérès, Jean-Jacques-Régis de, to Clarke, Duc de Feltre*, 3 April 1812; 1 leaf: "Monsieur le Duc, voici une dépêche télégraphique qui annonce un débarquement [britannique, a Corfou?]sans dire en quoi il consiste. Je prie Votre Excellence de me faire savoir quelle est son opinion... et si nous avons dans les isles des moiens suffisans de résistance." (Box 2, Folder 34b)
    - Cambon, Auguste, to General Paillard, 30 June 1808; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Cambon, Pierre Joseph, to the Procureur-Syndic of Paris, 30 May 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Campan, Madame, to Mademoiselle Cochelet, Lectrice to the Princess Louis Bonaparte, 4 Februray 1806; 1 leaf + 1 leaf+ 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 37)
      ALS in French (about one of the Princess' young protegée, and her admission into Mme Campan's school), plus translation.
    - Campan, Madame, to Mme Hottinguer, 28 May 1814; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 38)
      ALS in French (about one of the Hottinguers's young protegée, schooled in Mme Campan's institution), plus translation.
    - Canclaux, General Comte, to the Administrateurs des Hôpitaux militaires de Paris, 11 July 1796; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Carnot, Lazare, to the Commissaire Ordonnateur en Chef de l'Armée d'Italie, 28 May 1800; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Carnot, Lazare, to ?, 1796; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 2, Folder 41a)
      ALS in French, plus portraits of Carnot
    - Carnot, Lazare, to Fontanes, August 1813; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 41b)
      ALS in French: endorsement for a position of medical doctor in the Lycée militaire d'Autun
    - Caroline Bonaparte, former Queen of Naples, to Elisa-Napoléon Bonaparte-Baciocchi, Duchess of Lucca and Princess of Piombino, 7 April 1836; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 42)
      ALS in French, plus a portrait
    - Carteaux, Jean-Francois, to the Directeurs des Transports in Montpellier, 14 July 1793; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Document in French
    - Castries, Marquis Charles de la Croix de [Minister of the French Navy], to M. de Crèvecoeur, a.k.a. Hector St. John [First French Consul General in New York], 2 May 1784; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 44)
      ALS in French, about commerce issues, especially the facilities for French boats in New York City, and the French wine exports to the United States of America.
    - Castries, Marquis Charles de la Croix de [Minister of the French Navy], to M. de Roquefort, 7 July 1782; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Caulaincourt, Baron, 28 May 1814; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 46a)
      Passport delivered for M. Barral, plus portraits of Caulaincourt
    - Caulaincourt, Baron, to Baron Bignon*, 23 March 1819; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 46b)